# **Curriculum Vitae**

### KC Sivaramakrishnan

**Computer Laboratory** University of Cambridge

# January 17, 2016

San Jose, CA, USA

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

# Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

## Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Advisor: Daniel Waddington

Master of Science — Computer Science *Aug 2008 – May 2011* Purdue University, USA

GPA: 3.94/4 Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 - May 2008

PSG College of Technology GPA: 9.55/10 Anna University, India

# Experience

#### Research Associate, University of Cambridge Dec 2014 - present

Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Developing Multicore OCaml under the OCaml Labs initiative in the Computer Laboratory.

# Research Assistant, Purdue University

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014 Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

#### Teaching Assistant, Purdue University West Lafayette, IN, USA Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Aug 2012 - Dec 2012 Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) Aug 2011 – Dec 2011

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

#### Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge Feb 2012 - May 2012

Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

### Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D) May 2010 - Aug 2010

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language - a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

### Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Dec 2007 - Apr 2008 Advisor: Sankar Chnab Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

### Journal Publications

Workshop Publications

OCaml Workshop

W4

**Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects** 

Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy

#### **Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell** Nov 2015 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones J2 Accepted with minor revisions for Journal of Functional Programming (JFP) MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML Nov 2014 J1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 – 674 **Efficient Sessions** Feb 2013 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster J0 Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 – 167 Invited paper Conference Publications **Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores** Jun 2015 **C7** KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Rx-CML:** A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 **C6** KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL) A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C5 Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award **Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness** Jun 2012 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C4 International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM) **Composable Asynchronous Events** Jun 2011 **C**3 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction** June 2010 C2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION) **Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication** Sep 2009 C1 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)

Sep 2015

W3	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013
W2	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors  Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan  Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011
W1	The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop	Sep 2010
W0	Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads  KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan  Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)	Jan 2010
A Tachnical Paparts and Drafts		

## Technical Reports and Drafts

#### **Featherweight Threads for Communication**

Nov 2011

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan
Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018

# Teaching/Advising

• Guest Lectures:

T2

- Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent 2015–16.
- Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas 2015–16.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
  - Algorithms, Lent 2015–16.
  - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2015–16.
  - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2015–16.
  - Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
  - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
  - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:
  - James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Michelmas 2015 present.
  - Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js\_of\_ocaml, Sep 2015 present.
  - Theo Laurent, ENS de Lyon, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
  - Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

#### Talks

OCaml Platform: Update
OCaml Consortium Meeting
Paris, France

Multicore OCaml: Update
OCaml Developer's Meeting

Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects
OCaml Workshop 2015

Vancouver, Canada

**Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems** PhD Defense

Purdue University

Dec 2014

Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming

Invited Lecture

Mar 2014 Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony

PADL 2014

Jan 2014 San Diego, CA

Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud

ML Workshop 2013

Sep 2013 Boston, MA

A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC

**MARC 2012** 

Nov 2012 RWTH Aachen

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

ISMM 2012, Beijing

Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Jun 2012 May 2012

Lightweight Concurrency in GHC

Wrestling Wednesdays

May 2012

Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Jun 2012

**Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction** 

**COORDINATION 2012** 

CWI Amsterdam

## Professional Service

- Program Committee member: SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.

# Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.